hey it's Professor Dave let's talk about
carbon
science
Dave you may have heard that carbon is
the element of life but what does that
mean what determines whether an atom is
of carbon in the first place an atom
consists of positively charged protons
neutrons which have no charge and
negatively charged electrons an element
is defined by the number of protons in
the nucleus one proton is hydrogen two
is helium three lithium four burum five
Boron and six is carbon the number of
neutrons and electrons can change but by
definition any atom with six protons is
a carbon atom how do they form hydrogen
the simplest and most abundant of all
elements accumulates into clumps due to
gravity which becomes Stars the
tremendous inward pressure triggers
nuclear fusion which is when protons and
neutrons smash together in fuse many
elements including carbon and larger
ones like iron are made in Stars much
larger ones need the immense energy of a
supernova explosion or particle
accelerators here on Earth so what's so
special about carbon let's look at the
electrons carbon atoms have six the
first two are in the inner shell and the
other four are the so-called veence
electrons in the outer shell these are
the ones available for bonding with
other atoms which happens when two atoms
share two electrons because elements in
this part of the periodic table want to
have eight electrons in their outermost
shell carbon has a tendency to make four
bonds these can be single double or or
triple bonds and with many different
elements in addition while an atom
that's bound to two or three other atoms
will adopt a linear or flat shape a
carbon atom that's bound to four other
atoms will take on a three-dimensional
shape because that's how the electron
clouds on the four atoms can be as far
away from each other as possible so it's
the ability of carbon to bond in a wide
variety of shapes with so many elements
including itself that makes it so
special also carbon carbon bonds are
strong enough to be stable but not so
strong that they can't break and
rearrange which makes them excellent
building blocks when by itself carbon
has many allotropes or ways an element
can be arranged there's the graphite in
your pencil which consists of slippery
sheets of carbon that rub off easily
there's Diamond the hardest substance
known and we can even make interesting
structures like nanot tubes and
ferin that's just carbon by itself when
combined with hydrogen oxygen nitrogen
and a few other elements it makes all
the diverse structures in your body
including carbohydrates proteins and DNA
we can take nature a step further and
synthesize novel materials with an array
of purposes putting carbons in the empty
spots of an iron lattice makes it
stronger we call this steel which is
used in most of the large structures we
know today Teflon a carbon Florine
polymer is a non-stick substance that's
highly resistant to chemical degradation
and carbon-based synthetic drugs like
Inhibitors that can silence a faulty
enzyme hold the prospect of curing so
many diseases that's a lot of reasons to
love carbon it really is the element of
Life see you next time